<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Disease xmlns="tns:DiseaseSchema">
	<Meta>
		<ShortDescription>Malaria is a mosquito-borne infectious disease affecting humans and other animals caused by parasitic protozoans (a group of single-celled microorganisms) belonging to the Plasmodium type.[</ShortDescription>
		<WikiURL>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malaria</WikiURL>
	</Meta>
	<Names>
		<Name>Malaria</Name>
	</Names>
	<Specialties>
		<Speciality>Infectious</Speciality>
	</Specialties>
	<Relations>
		<Relation/>
	</Relations>
	<Symptoms>
		<Symptom>The classic symptom is paroxysm, a cyclical occurance of sudden coldness followed by shivering and then fever and sweating, occuring every 2-3 days.</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Fever</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Feeling tired</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Vomiting</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Shivering</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Joint Pain</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Hemolytic anemia</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Jaundice</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Hemoglobin in the urine</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Retinal damage</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Headaches</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Convulsions</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Early disease similar to flu-like symptoms</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Can resemble other conditions, such as sepsis, gastroenteritis, and viral diseases.</Symptom>
	</Symptoms>
	<Causes>
		<Cause>Bite by infected female Anopheles mosquito.</Cause>
		<Cause>Five species of parasitic Plasmodium protozoans</Cause>
		<Cause>Plasmodium falciparum causes the most deaths.</Cause>
	</Causes>
	<RiskFactors>
		<RiskFactor>Tropical regions around the equator, including sub-Saharan Africa, Asia, and Latin America.</RiskFactor>
	</RiskFactors>
	<Diagnostics>
		<Diagnostic>Recent travel history (for non-endemic areas)</Diagnostic>
		<Diagnostic>Enlarged spleen</Diagnostic>
		<Diagnostic>Fever</Diagnostic>
		<Diagnostic>Low number of platelets in the blood.</Diagnostic>
		<Diagnostic>Higher than normal levels of bilirubin in the blood.</Diagnostic>
		<Diagnostic>Confirm with microscopic examination of blood films or by antigen-based rapid diagnostic tests (RDT).</Diagnostic>
	</Diagnostics>
	<Treatments>
		<Treatment>Antimalarial medications, incl. artemisinins in combination with other anti-malarials, such as amodiaquine, lumefantrine, mefloquine, and others.</Treatment>
	</Treatments>
	<Prognoses>
		<Prognosis>When properly treated, people with malaria can usually expect a complete recovery.</Prognosis>
		<Prognosis>However, severe malaria can progress extremely rapidly and cause death within hours or days.</Prognosis>
		<Prognosis>In the most severe cases of the disease, fatality rates can reach 20%, even with intensive care and treatment.</Prognosis>
	</Prognoses>
</Disease>