<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Disease xmlns="tns:DiseaseSchema">
	<Meta>
		<ShortDescription>MRSA is any strain of S. aureus that has developed, through horizontal gene transfer and natural selection, multiple drug resistance to beta-lactam antibiotics</ShortDescription>
		<WikiURL>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methicillin-resistant_Staphylococcus_aureus</WikiURL>
	</Meta>
	<Names>
		<Name>Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus</Name>
		<Name>MRSA</Name>
	</Names>
	<Specialties>
		<Speciality>Skin</Speciality>
		<Speciality>Open Wounds</Speciality>
	</Specialties>
	<Relations>
		<Relation>Relation1</Relation>
	</Relations>
	<Symptoms>
		<Symptom>Small red bumps that resemble pimples, spider bites, or boils.</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Within a few days, red bumps become larger and more painful, and eventually open into deep, pus-filled boils.</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Fever</Symptom>
		<Symptom>Rash</Symptom>
	</Symptoms>
	<Causes>
		<Cause>Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) bacteria</Cause>
	</Causes>
	<RiskFactors>
		<RiskFactor>Indwelling implants, prostheses, drains or catheters</RiskFactor>
		<RiskFactor>Weak immune system</RiskFactor>
		<RiskFactor>Diabetics</RiskFactor>
		<RiskFactor>Intravenous drug users</RiskFactor>
	</RiskFactors>
	<Diagnostics>
		<Diagnostic>Bacterium culture from blood, urine, sputum, or other fluid samples</Diagnostic>
		<Diagnostic>Rapid latex agglutination test that detects PBP2a protein, which imparts MRSA's ability to resist oxacillin.</Diagnostic>
	</Diagnostics>
	<Treatments>
		<Treatment>Treatment is urgent, and delays can be fatal.</Treatment>
		<Treatment>Location and history related to the infection determines the treatment.</Treatment>
		<Treatment>Both CA-MRSA and HA-MRSA are resistant to traditional anti-staphylococcal beta-lactam antibiotics, such as cephalexin</Treatment>
		<Treatment>CA-MRSA has a greater spectrum of antimicrobial susceptibility to sulfa drugs (like co-trimoxazole (trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole), tetracyclines (like doxycycline and minocycline) and clindamycin (for osteomyelitis).[</Treatment>
		<Treatment>MRSA can be eradicated with a regimen of linezolid,[85] though treatment protocols vary and serum levels of antibiotics vary widely person to person and may affect outcomes.[</Treatment>
		<Treatment>The effective treatment of MRSA with linezolid has been successful[85] in 87% of people. Linezolid is more effective in soft tissue infections than vancomycin.</Treatment>
	</Treatments>
	<Prognoses>
		<Prognosis/>
	</Prognoses>
</Disease>